software engineering radio episode 12
concurrency part 1
[Music]
hello everybody welcome to this new
episode of software engineering radio
this is the first of several episodes on
concurrency however before we start with
the topic we have to make sure that we
announce the winner of the book as a
revolt for the feedback you give us and
the winner of the remoting patterns book
is john rod lei will contact you John in
the next couple of days or weeks to make
sure we ship this book somehow to you
please continue giving us feedback if
possible give us the feedback through
the comments facility on the se- Radio
dotnet website so other people can see
what you think about the podcast so
let's get on to the topic concurrency
this first episode is handled by Misha
ale and Aleks the idea for this episode
stands from listener feedback and it's
on the foundation of concurrency we will
lay the very basics in this episode the
following episodes will deal with more
advanced topics so what does concurrency
in software and in software development
in general mean basically it means that
we have a computer that does more than
one thing
at the same time in the simple case of
course more than one application at the
same time and concurrency can be
achieved physically which means we have
more than one hardware execution unit
more than one CPU for example such as in
modern multi-core CPUs or server
machines but it also means that it's
simulated through software where
concurrency is not real concurrency
where some things happen at the exact
same time but it's the switching between
the applications is so fast that we get
the impression of really concurrent
running threats or applications almost
all modern operating system offers
support for multitasking and
multi-threading which is the basic of
concurrency we'll deal with the
terms bit later and define them but also
infrastructures like application servers
little machines of a concurrency support
so we have it in different layers of the
stack infrastructure stack today this
means for programs that we have to deal
with concurrency we have stuff like
threading libraries PT thread library
for example we have to for processes to
get concurrency so there are api's to
create new processes threads and to deal
with concurrency issues yeah we asked
ourselves so why is it important why's
concurrency today so important and we
discovered two reasons for that the
first is performance and the second is
scalability and efficiency yeah and
performance is of course the most
obvious you have a task that just takes
too long for one single machine to
compute there are the classic examples
like weather simulation where a single
CPU is just not fast enough to to deal
with a huge amount of stuff to do so we
have to to deal with this problem we
have to find algorithms that divide the
problem into smaller parts to make
separation on different CPUs possible to
use multi CPU cluster systems so that it
can the results can be computed in
parallel for this you have to find new
or different algorithms let's solve the
problem in parallel otherwise you
wouldn't get and benefit from an other
additional CPU so that's a pretty
complex topic beside the weather
examples you can find this in financial
services for example there are huge
simulations running that simply would
take too long on a single CPU so the
algorithms have to be affected or or
written differently to support multiple
CPUs if you just want to to get a
feeling for this try to compare the
different sorting algorithms bubble sort
immerse or the quicksort how could you
splited or really sign them to run in
parallel on different CPUs it's not very
trivial problem it's actually pretty
hard stuff fortunately a lot of problems
are symmetrical or parallel by nature if
you take the multi-user stuff you can
easily parallel the the single tasks per
user you don't have to find a new
algorithm to solve the problem a lot of
graphical programs are easily
parallelizable and like ray-tracing for
example you can easily put this on a
multi-core or multi super machine but
that's just for performance we also have
scalability regarding scalability the
idea is to split the application and put
it on several CPUs or even to use one
CPU more efficiently and the problem
with efficiency is that the CPU has
nothing to do while we wait for user
input or network input or disk i/o and
for this it's a good idea to design the
application using concurrency so that we
can make best use of the CPU resources
not waiting not wasting time while we
wait for i/o operations now exactly we
also have to deal with a different
problem or an additional problem the
speed increase of modern CPUs will not
only be reached by simply raising or
increasing the clock speed it this gets
more and more difficult because we have
physical limits there so most or all
modern CPUs have some kind of parallel
processing in it and you heard all the
bus about multi-core CPUs and that's
another thing you have to deal with as
programmer because you have to really
program or write your program that the
different cores are used so there is a
very very good article on this and you
can find it on the web and we put the
URL on our website the free lunch is
over which describes exactly that
problem that
cpos will not get the speed increase
simply by hires clock speeds and that
you as a programmer have to deal with it
that we have to or that concurrency and
programming for concurrency gets more
and more important the next years so
before we go to the real programming
issues and how you have to program it I
guess we should clarify some terminology
some terms and the first are or the very
basic terms are multitasking pre-emptive
multitasking versus cooperative
multitasking when concurrency was
introduced most computers still had one
CPU but the applications had to wait
very long for for i/o operations to
finish because CPUs always were were lot
faster than the iOS typically operating
system programmers introduced first
multi programming and then multitasking
to to deal with the problem as Mihail
already mentioned you can better use
your cpu resources if you don't have to
wait for i/o by just using the cpu for
other stuff so multi programming was
very clever idea to do this the
operating system has a schedule which
switched between the different tasks and
it did this so fast that they seemed to
run in parallel actually they didn't run
parallel because you just have one CPU
but it seemed like they were running in
parallel first then we had some kind of
cooperative multitasking where the task
has to set themselves asleep if they did
an i/o operation for example or if they
just we're ready to wait and so the the
single programs did cooperate and free
resources for others to run you might
remember earlier Windows versions that
help this kind of multitasking
implemented of this has some flaws
because of course if your application
doesn't free the CPU and no other
we'll ever run so there is an other kind
of multitasking which is called
pre-emptive multitasking which almost
all operating systems at least I know
support today where the operating system
actually interrupts the running program
after a specified time slice so it
doesn't have to use or the singing
programs doesn't have to cooperate the
operating system does the chop and thus
a fear well a fair scheduling of the
single task so in the context of
multitasking and multi-threading what
are actually threats and processes yep
first we had processes a process is a
single execution unit program that runs
in parallel to two other processes and
there are a lot of features that a
process has that makes it heavy weight
or let's define heavy weight a bit more
first of all you have a separate address
space that means your program has its
own address space and can't read or
write the data from another process
there is a physical type in your CPU
which is most often called MMO memory
managing unit which does this protection
it actually checks if your read or
writes go in your address space or not
and the application actually has the
image or it actually feels like you have
your own address space complete and the
complete address space is just yours
there this is very complex thing in
operating systems where the physical
address in the memory and the virtual
address are separated that's pretty
complex but the main point is you have a
protection of you process not to harm
any other process that runs on the
operating systems the bad thing of this
is of course context which is between
this processes and all the stuff you
have to do for this is very expensive
expensive in the sense of it costs a lot
of
time to switch the context between these
different processes and the other thing
is process of course have to communicate
with each others because they live in
the same infrastructure and there is
stuff they have to talk with each others
and this inter process communication is
also very very expensive because it has
to go around all this protection
mechanisms so there was this this other
thing called threat yeah threats are
more lightweight than processes and
cheered the different threats run
actually in the same address space so
they can access each other's data they
have all the data in common unless it's
explicitly separated between the threats
OS designers invented threats after
processes to have a parallel execution
of code within the same process the bad
thing about threads is that they don't
provide any protection for data
corruption so if there's one misbehaving
thread it can corrupt the data of all
other threats the good thing about
threads is that the context switch of
the CPU switching between threads is
more lightweight is cheaper and there
are no interpreters communication
barriers the communication between
threads is much easier much faster there
are some differences in threat
implementations between UNIX and Windows
but nowadays you can say in general they
are more lightweight than processors
there is a similar term related to a
thread that is a task and the term task
is often used in the context of
real-time operating systems such as
VxWorks
and toss typically don't have their own
address base in that regard they are
similar to threats and one of the
reasons they they are called tasks and
not processes is because they run
typically on Hardware that has no memory
management you
and so because of that they have
actually no chance to to protect their
address spaces now that we have the
operating system in place which does all
the the multi processing multitasking
multi threading stuff for us what is
actually difficult dealing with
concurrency where are the problems yeah
the hardest part and the most
challenging is they exist to shared
resources those resources can be any
devices of a computer that can also be
memory locations or the database and
second hard part is how to achieve
actually a performance improvement and
not end up with a locked up application
and dozens of hidden race conditions and
and corrupted data at the end and the
third hard topic is adapting algorithms
to work in parallel and to synchronize
at the end of the parallel threads
processes for the final result okay and
how can we as programmers keep them in
consistence they work what are the other
tools we we got to to do this yeah an
important term here is the critical
section and in programming a critical
section is a piece of code that can only
be executed by one process or thread at
a time and in that critical section we
actually access the shared resources
another term and really elementary
concept of concurrency Harv's semaphores
they are not used so much today mostly
in in today's programming we use mutexes
and locks which we will explain in a in
a second and semaphores
are basically protected variables and
they allow to restrict access to shared
resources they manage the entrance of
critical sections
and there are typically in pretty
elementary way of OS implementations to
provide synchronization between
processes and threats and the simplest
kind of semaphore is a binary semaphore
which is used to for just what I said
to measure sexes of a single resource
and a binary semaphore is basically the
same as a lock or also called mutex
they're both similar concepts and the
log is used in a way that when a thread
once ended a critical section it gets
the log does something inside a critical
section when it leaves it will release
the log again and no other process a
thread is allowed to enter that critical
section while another threat or process
holds the lock mm-hmm what problems
might occur on in practical programming
applications with this stuff it gives
examples on yeah
one of the hardest topic and really
painful problems is a race condition a
race condition happens when you have
inconsistent data because of overlapping
parallel executing threads many
blading-- the same shared resource and
leaving it in an inconsistent state yeah
and other well it's not really a
different kind of part but what makes
working with concurrency pretty hard is
what we call Heisenberg box which means
you have a problem and if you for
example debug the problem or enter some
print lines in your algorithm the
problem disappears so it because you're
you're debugging or you're logging or
whatever changes the speed of execution
the problem is not you it disappears
actually so you can't reproduce it it's
still there of course because didn't
disappear but you changed
the behavior changed because of you
looked at it so it's a bit like this
quantum physics Heisenberg stuff yeah
another hard problem are dead logs and
dead logs happened for example when a
threat forgets to release the lock or
even more difficult when you have two
threats and thread a gets the log asked
threat beat for something and Freddie
also needs the same log to answer the
request but threat B will never get to
acquired a lot and thread a will never
get its response to result from threat B
and deadlock nothing moves forward
nothing moves backward the program just
freezes so but why should I care about
concurrency in which domains do I get in
touch with concurrency you have
concurrency in all the layers or all the
layers you have to deal with offer some
kind of currency today CPUs do they have
multi course parallel pipelines and all
that stuff operation system offer
concurrency they have this processes
threats with the machines actually do an
infrastructure like servlet engines each
enterprise javabeans whatever there are
a lot of well infrastructures like web
service that also offer concurrency what
is pretty comfortable some of these
height the the concurrency topics away
from the developer so as a normal each
a/b developer you should not have to
care about the concurrency stuff because
the concurrency is embedded in the
architecture of EJB so it's hidden away
from you so it's the same like if you
write a very simple program without any
concurrency you don't have to deal with
concurrency offered by the operating
system that it's a multi-user
multitasking operating system it's just
hidden away we beyond so current
currencies everywhere and you have
sometimes to deal with it sometimes not
so much yeah
regarding application domains
we found three key domains where you
have to do a hardcore concurrency
programming and the first one is
developing infrastructures like
application servers component containers
where you want to provide some level of
concurrency but you want to shield also
the component developers from all the
concurrency difficulties and because of
that you have to do all the work and
keep the component data in and the
component state in a consistent state
secondly developing embedded
applications you are mostly faced with a
lot of concurrency for example in the
automation domain when you control and
monitor multiple devices or an
infotainment system where you have to
gather GPS information for navigation
where you have to visualize the current
speed of the car and provide at the same
time entertainment functionality the
third big domain our databases databases
or shared resources by nature and here
the concurrency is managed through
so-called transactions transactions are
in that sense similar to logs similar to
critical regions where no concurrency or
in the leaving threads of processes
should occur and manipulate the data
yeah and to talk a bit more or specific
about a concrete example let's take a
look at the Java Virtual Machine as a
container the java virtual machine
actually offers concurrency and java
itself goes so far that it has some
construct the synchronized keyword in
the language that helps you dealing with
concurrency and synchronizes one of this
stuff we will talk about one of the
following episodes I guess synchronized
it's actually an implementation of a
monitor which is one of these how do I
protect my critical section things
but we will talk about this later so the
Whittle machine offers multi-threading
within the Brittain machine and it might
depend on the actually on the operating
system the rotary machine operates or
runs on but it also has its own
implementation of multi-threading green
threads from the people who used it ever
whether with a machine does all the the
scheduling stuff itself to be
independent of the running on other
operating system it runs on so if you
deal with concurrency in the Java
Virtual Machine you actually might not
really be sure which layer be below thus
the concurrency because sometimes the or
most of the time the rotor machine
delegates the concurrency to the
operating system because then it can use
more than one CPU otherwise it would the
virtual machine would be seen as one
single process from the operating system
and so it can't be paralyzed to more
than one CPU so it's sometimes important
to know how the layers below or the
layers that offer you the concurrency
features actually implement concurrency
to get the speed of your heart or the
parallelism of your hardware you use
okay that's it for this episode we want
to give a quick outlook of the next
episodes and the following episodes we
will talk about synchronization and
concurrency in detail what patterns are
there what are the best practices for
synchronization and concurrency and then
the next one of the next episodes we
will also talk about how to build highly
scalable servers
[Music]
this was another episode of software
engineering radio the software
engineering radio team wants to thank
Henning poly for providing the music as
well as Lipson comm for hosting in
bandwidth for more information on the
podcast past episodes and feedback go to
s e - radio dotnet
[Music]